Download the My Hangingham app today and
report issues and get information on
town government with ease. Available on
the App Store and Google Play. You can
submit service requests or gain
information with just a few taps on your
phone. Using the My Hanga map puts
immediate access to town resources in
the palm of your hand, including
calendars of meetings and events,
agendas for upcoming meetings, building
permit filing options, online bill
payment options, and info about our
boards, committees, departments, and
services.
For more information, please scan the QR
code on your screen.
>> [music]
>> Good evening. This meeting of the select
board is called to order on August 25th,
2026 at 6:02 p.m.
This meeting is being held in person
and/or remotely as an alternate means of
public access pursuant to chapter 2 of
the acts of 2025 and all other
applicable laws temporarily amending
certain provisions of the open meeting
law. You are hereby advised that this
meeting and all communications during
this meeting may be recorded by the town
of Hangingham in accordance with the
open meeting law. If any participant
wishes to record this meeting, please
notify the chair at the start of the
meeting in accordance with Mass General
Law Chapter 30A section 20F so that the
chair may inform all other participants
of said recording. Is anyone recording
the meeting this evening?
Great. I will state [clears throat] for
the record participating this evening
myself Liz Klein chair Julie Staley and
Bill Ramsay. If you're willing and able,
please stand for the pledge of
allegiance.
I pledge algiance to the flag of the
United States of America and to the
republic for which it stands. One nation
under God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
>> Next on the agenda is approval of
minutes. Believe we have a few sets.
>> You ready to proceed?
>> I'm ready.
>> Okay. Make a motion to approve the
minutes dated July 7th, 2026.
>> Second.
>> Roll call vote. Julie
>> I.
>> Bill.
>> And I'm an I as well.
>> I'll make a motion to approve the
minutes deate uh dated July 21st, 2026.
>> Second.
>> Roll call vote. Julie.
>> I.
>> Bill.
>> I'm an and I as well.
>> I make a motion to approve the minutes
dated July 29th, 2026.
>> Second.
>> Roll call vote. Julie.
>> I.
>> Bill.
>> I am. And I as well.
I'll make a motion to approve the
minutes dated August 11th, 2026.
>> Second.
>> Roll call vote. Julie
>> I.
>> Bill.
>> I am an I as well. Thank you. Next on
the agenda is executive session under
Mass General Law Chapter 30A section
21A3
to discuss strategy with respect to
collective bargaining with Teamsters
Local Union 25 DPW supervisors.
Before I entertain a motion to go into
executive session under item four of the
agenda, I hereby declare that discussion
of this agenda item in an open session
may have a detrimental effect on the
bargaining position of the public body.
I make a motion to enter executive
session under Mass General Law Chapter
30A section 21A3 to conduct strategy
with respect to collective bargaining
with Teamsters Local Union 25 DPW
supervisors. The board will reconvene in
open session. I'll second that motion.
>> Roll call vote. Julie
>> I.
>> Bill.
>> And I'm an I as well. So, we're going
into executive session. We will be back
shortly.
[clears throat] Thank you for everyone's
patience. Uh we are now returning to
open session. Next on the agenda is
potential vote to sign the memorandum of
agreement with Teamsters local union 25
DPW supervisors.
We have Ashley Ber, you want to come on
up? And Jack [clears throat] Manning and
Lyn Carol.
[clears throat]
[cough and laughter]
Oh, sorry. I I have to Sorry, I didn't
do this. The board has completed its
executive session and is now convening
back in open session and will now take
up the next item on the agenda. The
potential vote to sign the memorandum of
agreement with Teamsters local union
25DW supervisors.
>> Do we have to vote on that?
>> No.
>> Sorry. Thank you.
>> Hi.
Um, so
we were able to uh negotiate a new
contract with our supervisors as a
three-year contract that will go through
um at 2029.
Um, and we were pass that out pretty
quickly with not a huge increase
to the budget. Um, and I believe
everyone's pretty happy with the outcome
on both sides.
Excellent. Jack or Lyn, do you want to
add anything?
>> Sure. Um, it was a it was a great
bargaining session. Uh, we got it done
two meetings which is rare. Um, and a
lot of us do Ashley did a wonderful job
getting us all prepared before we even
hit the ground in our first meeting as
well as Tom. Great support from from
everyone. Katie helped as well. Um, went
into the session not expecting anything
not other than okay, what are they going
to be asking for? There were about 15 16
asks that the the union made of us. 11
or 12 of them had money attached to
them. Um we ended up agreeing to some of
them and not to others. Uh all in all
the biggest item of course is going to
be salary. Uh so they came out of the
box uh asking for 55 and five. Um which
is way outside of the kind of numbers
that we were prepared to bargain with
and they knew that. Um, we settled at
the 33 and three uh for the the contract
term. Um, some of the other items that
were in there, there were some ads, the
longevity, clothing allowances,
some stipens uh per phone and a few
other things, but as Ashley just uh
referred to, total cost from a monetary
perspective about 19,000 maybe 195 in
terms of dollars. Uh and then in
percentage terms, if you take out one
item regarding a phone, which really is
a one-time item, so to speak, uh in the
sense that we only have four members of
that union as it is, um it was a big
piece of the dollar impact and a big
piece of percentage, but if you took
that one item out, we were slightly
below 3.5% is what we came in at.
>> Yeah.
>> So, it was within the terms that you had
given us to work with. Uh we were
grateful that uh they were serious about
talking. Um they understood we had
constraints that we could go so far but
we couldn't do everything. Um and we
have a strong relationship working
relationship with uh the team
representative. So it really helped us
get the negotiation.
>> Excellent. Yes, it certainly showed.
Thank you Ashley for your leadership. Um
that is obvious and certainly paved the
way for it to go smoothly it sounds
like. And thank you Jack and Lynn for
all of your efforts. You get a record
that it was in two sessions. So
appreciate um the DPW supervisors for
being so collaborative as well um and
all of their hard work um day in and day
out. Um I am in supportive of of the
agreement. I think it shows how much we
value them. We think it's very fair. Um
so I have no no issues. Bill, do you
have any questions?
>> No question. Just thank you Ashley
Jacqueline. Um, thank you to the DPW
leadership as well and we have a
fantastic uh DPW in this town um that
work really hard for our residents and
do some tough jobs. So, very
appreciative of everything and I think
the contract reflects it. So, thank you
>> Julie.
>> I'll just echo the thanks um the
building is offered to everyone
negotiation. So, thank you and it's a
good contract and it's ready to go.
Okay, any comments or questions for
members of the public?
Okay, I'm ready to take a motion.
Want to
>> go? Sure.
>> I'll make a motion to sign the
memorandum of agreement with Teamsters
local 25 DPW supervisors effective July
1st, 2026 through June 30th, 2029.
>> Second.
>> Roll call vote. Julie
>> I.
>> Bill.
>> And I'm as well. Thank you so much.
>> Thank you guys so much.
>> Thanks a lot.
Next on the agenda is to consider
approval of a special one-day wine and
malt beverages licensed to Eric
Christensen for the River Rock Music
Festival at Weir River Farm to be held
on Saturday, September 12th, 2026 from
1:30 p.m. to 7:30 p.m.
You guys see Eric? And should we have
Heather with us?
>> Yes. Okay,
Heather Eric, do you can you tell us a
little bit about the event?
>> Sure. I'll I'll um I'm the development
director at Friendship Home and first of
all, thank you for inviting us here to
talk about this a little bit. Um this
will be the sixth annual River Rock
Music Fest that we have held. Um, it
started off in someone's yard actually
on the North River in Norwell and we've
grown it so much that we really needed a
much bigger venue and we were very
fortunate to find Rever Farm. It's a
beautiful, beautiful place that holds
the amount of people that we need to
have there and they've been just very
gracious for this event. Um, it's one of
our most beloved fundraisers actually at
this point in time and it's it's our
most inclusive event. Um, we are raising
money for Friendship Home in Norwell
which helps people with developmental
disabilities and um we're just really
fortunate to be able to share this um
information about this event with you.
But I can answer any questions that you
may have to. I don't want to keep going
on but I have a lot of wonderful things
to say about it.
>> Excellent. Well, thank you for all that
you do. Um, I see the application is in
order. It looks like the um, police
chief Jones has signed off and is
requiring one detail officer uh, to help
with parking, I'm assuming.
>> Um, I did just want to clarify the um,
the the license is for Erica
Christensen or is it Eric?
Eric. [clears throat]
Eric.
Okay.
>> Okay. Perfect. Do you have any
questions, Julie?
>> Um, well, the tip certification is for
Erica.
>> Yeah, that's that's for
>> correct.
>> Oh, okay. Is that is that correct? I
just want to make sure we don't have a
typo in the language.
>> Uh, that's correct. Yes.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. Thank you for clarifying.
>> Did you have any questions or comments?
>> Uh, no. Just waiting.
>> Okay.
>> Bill, any questions or comments?
>> Uh, no questions. Thank you. Good luck
with the event.
>> Thank you very much.
>> Any questions or comments for members of
the public?
>> Okay. Ready to take a motion? I make a
motion to approve the issuance of a
special one-day wine and malt beverages
license to Eric Christensen for the
River Rock Music Festival [snorts] at
Wear River Farm to be held on Saturday,
September 12th, 2026 from 1:30 p.m. to
7:30 p.m.
>> Second roll call vote. Julie
>> I,
>> Bill,
>> I.
>> And I'm as well. Thank you so much. Good
luck with the event.
>> Thank you.
Next on the agenda is discussion and
potential vote regarding opening the
warrant and insertion of warrant
articles into the warrant and to close
the warrant for the 2026 special town
meeting.
Do we have Laura Burns or Tom Moran? I
see HMLP.
Laura.
>> Hi Laura. How are you?
>> I'm fine. How are you?
>> Very well.
>> So I'm sorry I 479 Main Street for the
light work. I missed a few sentences
there um because I had to get in and
>> Sorry. Can we get
>> I know I was gonna say I can't
>> very well. I can hear a little bit.
Wonder if the volume can be adjusted.
>> Okay.
>> So, where are we?
>> Thanks, Sebastian.
>> Go ahead, Laura.
>> So, but just tell me where what where we
are
>> still.
Sebastian, can you increase it just a
little bit?
>> Okay.
I don't know if she can do it. Um, so we
we just got to the agenda item
discussion and potential vote regarding
opening the warrant and insertion of the
warrant articles. So, do you want to um
give us an update on the HMLP warrant
article?
>> Okay, sure. Happy to. So, we just uh
finished a meeting um and um board
member Julie Streley was there and um
where we are is uh contrary to my hope
that u you know where we were was
um after town meeting we were awaiting
uh our rate study so that we could look
at the costs going forward and go back
to the public with an accurate picture
of
what rate increases would be required in
order to complete our project.
And the hope was that we would get the
rate study. There it is. There's the
answer. We could come right back to the
select board and the advisory committee
and say, "Here's what it is." We're not
there yet. We don't have the numbers.
Um, I don't want to bore you with
uh where we've been, but the main reason
that we're not there yet is because when
we saw first saw the rate study, um the
rate increases that were indicated that
were needed to complete this project
were not acceptable to the board. So, we
have been working uh we've been meeting
every week working with our consultants
to find ways to bring down the cost of
this project to the rateayers.
And uh so we've uh we're exploring a
number of changes in how we're going to
finance this uh project which we hope
will accomplish that. But we we can't
present the full picture yet because at
this moment we're waiting on Eversource
to bring us a new proposal about how we
would finance the piece that uh is the
tap station that Eversource will own.
and they said they might have uh
information by the end of this week. But
uh it still leaves the board with a lot
of uh variables to juggle and without
all the data that we need to juggle them
and and choose a way forward and say
okay this is this is the way forward and
we feel like we need to have that to
present to you to the advisory committee
to the public. um and time is growing
short for that and we can't actually say
once again when we'll be able to come
forward with that information. So, as a
result, we had a conversation about
postponing uh the vote on the bonding
for the project and concluded and voted
to uh request the select board to to
tell the select word that we wish to
withdraw our request that you put the
bonding article on the forum. And uh the
reason is that we hope to come back in
the spring and we we will obviously have
all of these. It was it was always a
short timeline to to get the numbers in
order and if all had looked beautiful
when we got the first report we could
have done that and uh but uh we are
working really hard to try to try to
bring the cost down and we're we haven't
decided on what the best report is uh
way to go forward is but by the spring
we will by you know by late fall we will
certainly have the answer on what what
it is exactly we want to propose But at
at this moment we can't tell you what
that will be and we can't tell the
advisory committee and our feeling is
that time is too short to ask you and
the advisory committee to wait for that
proposal and then have time to evaluate
it. That said, um we uh one of the one
of the as I think you know, one of the
proposals that we are pursuing is um
asking the legislature for a home
petition to allow us to bond uh the
entire project for 30 years instead of
20 years, which will uh bring down the
yearly cost of the project considerably.
Um so uh we have voted tonight to
forward to you an article that's been
approved as a form by the town council
to uh ask town meeting to ask the
swatboard to ask our state
representatives to petition the
legislature to allow us to bond for 30
years and we are not required to um to
bond for 30 years. if we uh win that
right through the legislature, it will
it will be an option that we'll have um
to help bring the cost down. So, that
was one of our ideas, one that we've
been working on. So, I bring you that
article and I think you probably have
the have the um the text.
>> Yes.
>> And that's pretty much where we are. So,
I I'm happy to answer any questions you
might have.
>> Okay. Well, thank you Laura and thank
you Tom and the entire light board for
your diligence and persistence. Um, and
Laura, appreciate the cander and in
terms of the the status right now. Um, I
think we, as you mentioned, we don't
have enough information in front of us
to make a really good decision and be
prepared for October. So, um, I
appreciate your your suggestion. Um,
Julie, any questions or comments?
>> Um, thank you, Laura. Thank you, Tom.
And um I thank the whole um light board
that has been working really hard to and
the staff at the HMLP to crunch the
numbers and find all the ways to um
present the numbers, get all the detail
and data needed for this project. But um
that takes time and I think it's
important to get all the information and
have that information in hand and no
changes and so then it can be presented
well to the voters and um for success of
this project. Um I support capital
improvement to our electric
infrastructure. Um I have a question
about um the state sighting board and if
you could just mention their final
report when you expect that to come in
and what information um that would be
useful coming out of that report.
>> Um yes would you like to give I may get
the exact dates wrong. Um just please
state your name and address.
>> Tom Moran, general manager of Ham
Municipal Lighting Plant. Uh the
sighting board is expected to give a uh
an informal ruling somewhere around the
21st of uh September that'll go to all
uh petitioners that were uh involved in
the project.
There'll be a uh in-person meeting on
Monday the 28th
and based on uh you know everyone will
have an opportunity to speak at that
meeting and then based on uh the outcome
of that meeting we should have a uh
proposed approval but it takes 30 it'll
be a 30-day waiting period before it
becomes effective. So we again on the
28th we should have something in hand
that uh that says the project hopefully
is approved.
>> Okay, great. And then besides the
approval, is there any information in
the report that you would that would be
helpful going forward um in the future
um to give to voters?
uh the the the whole the the whole uh
sighting board case is is online and uh
if you go to our website hir.com
you'll find that um that filing and the
need project need is all listed in that
project. Um and again the the sighting
board has been doing this for you know
30 years. Um they'll look at the need
for the project. to look at the cost of
the project and they'll make a decision
on whether this project should go
forward or not. Um there should be
enough there for anyone to uh to read
and go through and and make a you know
informed decision.
>> Well, and also we'll be able to pull
stuff out of it um to answer people's
questions about why is this project
needed.
>> Yeah. Again, we we'll go, you know, once
we do go before we go for approval,
again, you know, our plan would be to
have uh, you know, public sessions to
um socialize the project uh with
everyone in town as we as we've done in
the past.
>> Okay. Thank you. Um, and as far as the
special legislation request, I just want
to thank you all for exploring any ways
to decrease the rates and finding
creative ways to to um to finance um the
project and um it makes sense. I think
it makes sense to ask for this option.
So
>> great. Thank you, Bill.
>> I don't have any questions. Just want to
uh thank the light board. I know this is
a very important project. Um, it's also
complicated
and I appreciate your continued due
diligence um on this um on this effort
here. So, we'll see you um see you for
the spring. Thank you.
>> Excellent. Thank you. Any questions or
comments from members of the public?
>> Okay. Um
and we're going to go to number nine and
do the presentation right before taking
this vote.
>> Um so we will we'll bring up the
presentation and let them let Angela and
present um both PRS.
>> Okay.
>> Um then we'll have to motion
for our page open
the two articles on BRS and HMLP that we
just covered. you close the warrant and
then we'll identify the nine which is
slightly different authorizing new
design.
>> Okay. So, Angela,
>> do you all want to come up? Aisha Katie.
So, we're going a little out of order,
but thought it would be helpful for
people to have this context in the
school building committee update before
we take the vote.
>> Sounds good.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you. Um, I'm Angela here
representing the 2025 school building
committee. Um, I'm here joined by
Superintendent Roberts and Aisha Opang
as well from the Hangingham School
District. And online we may have John
Kuski who is the I'm sorry her pesky um
and he is the design lead from Gail.
Great technical questions.
So, um I we submitted to you the updated
version of the 2025 school building
committee update that we shared also
with um the school committee at ADCOM.
Um so it does have some context slides
um just about the process and then our
schematic side packages. Um and just as
optional information for you, we also
did include the HVAC options just as an
update. Great. Um on the next slide is
just a shot of the MSBA process as
you'll recall. Um when we spoke before
we were at the beginning of schematic
design and at this point we are at the
end of schematic design for the
elementary school groups and in the
middle of schematic design for the high
school.
Uh so in the next slide um this is just
that summary slide for the high school
I'm sorry for the elementary school
rooms. Um, and what I'll share with you
today is the schematic design package
high level. On the next slide,
um, I'll go through quickly what the
design team found as existing conditions
at South Elementary School. First off,
South um, was originally built in 1948.
Um, and then there was an addition in
um, 1990,
I'm sorry, in the 1950s and 1990s. So,
there's two main roof systems. One is a
steep slope asphalt shingle, and that's
in that bottom left um, original 1948
build. Um, and then in the upper right,
um, portion of the building is a low
slope EPDM membrane roof. Um so existing
conditions found um significant um areas
of water infiltration with staining both
above and at the ceiling tiles. Um the
asphalt shingles are in um fair to poor
condition. Um and many portions are
already patched um past its useful life.
Um and there is some buckling and
deterioration of many of the um
shingles.
Um and then throughout both in the EPDM
portion and throughout um the shingled
areas, there's areas of flashing which
is like the protective barrier where the
roofing materials meet the the walls or
building. Um and much of the flashing is
peeled back which is actually where some
of the water exposure is coming from as
well. Um and areas of deteriorated or
damaged masonry as well identified.
Um additionally um there was a
structural evaluation for what the um
existing structural can support. Um and
there were two findings. one was that in
the 1948
section
that the framing for that part of the
roof is all original 1948
timber.
Um so the design team did determine that
that does not meet current code. So
reinforcement of those areas will be
required. Um and then in the middle um
the middle of the back portion um right
along the middle section of that middle
section there's a band that just meets
code. So it's at 99%
loading of of the capacity that that
part of the framing can hold. And the
design team recommends
um keeping
loading at at 90%. Um at the most. So
their recommendation is to um also
reinforce that section as well.
Um and then I'll go to the next slide. I
kind of gave you a little bit about the
recommendations up front. Um but the
designs team team's overall
recommendation is to do a full roof
replacement. Um and the recommended or
the selected materials um for the steep
slope area um is replacing the asphalt
shingles with a standing seam metal
roof.
Um and for the low slope areas that
current have currently have an EPDM
membrane um the recommendation is an 80
mil PVC for low slope.
Um, and I will highlight that there were
options both more expensive and less
expensive than what was selected. So,
this is solidly
a a solid middle option. Um, we did
evaluate if we did go one step lower in
terms of roofing quality. Um the
difference in price was about $180,000,
but the difference in quality was 10
years less um lifespan and warranty
timing. So instead of a a 30-year
warranty, we'd be going down to a
20-year warranty. And that also does
affect the actual roofing material. So
the actual expected life does decrease
as well. So um that was one area where
the school building committee felt that
that additional
180,000 was worth the 10 years of
additional lif span. Um the other
recommendations were replacing and
correcting the flashing in the gutters
and also masonry repairs.
Um, and then the seal, the structural
reinforcements, which I already alluded
to, was reinforcing that original 1940
timber that is required. Um, and then
reinforcing the middle portion of the
that back building would be um a steel
reinforcement. And the committee did
evaluate technically it just meets code.
if we did not do that upgrade, what
would the class difference be? And that
was $340,000.
Um, and then we also deliberated that um
if we didn't do that work and in the
future if we added RTUs or something
happened where any weight was added to
that roof, we would be responsible for
the full amount. Whereas if we take care
of it now while we're already replacing
the roof, we have that area exposed. We
can do that work. We also have the MSBA
grant that um that structural
reinforcement would bring it up to solar
ready. So the MSBA could also help
reimburse
for that structural work. So as a
committee we felt that um it was worth
doing now rather [snorts] than doing
later um especially given that it is
above 90%
um and that we could have the MSP
reimbursement in that
um so those were the um that was the
recommendations and then the committee's
deliberation. Just to summarize the
overall costs, the next slide has
specifically the construction breakdown.
Um that roofing system replacement comes
to about 5 million. Um since we are
above the 30%
since the project value is above 30% of
the building's value, we also do have to
do um MAB accessibility upgrades to
bring the building fully up to MAB code.
Um and then the structural modifications
and ceiling scope those that um about
900,000 combined are for both of
structural rein reinforcements the two
areas that I mentioned and then the
masonry and flashing repairs are for the
mason masonry and and fixing and sealing
up edges of flashing. So the overall
construction estimate comes to 6.9
million. And then the next slide has the
overall budget summary that adds in our
current schematic design. So that top
line is what we've already spent so far.
Um and then architecture and OPM going
forward is the second line. we have the
construction miscellaneous proc um
project costs um for an overall budget
including contingencies of 8.2 million.
And so that is the total project budget
that um the school building committee
and the school committee have approved
and that we're seeking approval for to
um
uh submit as our schematic design
budget.
Any questions on south before I go to
I don't have any questions. Julie,
>> ask a quick question about the budget.
Um, so the town meeting 2025
appropriated the 181600.
>> Um, it was actually 300.
>> It was 300,000.
>> Okay. So the total cost project budget
that you would go to town meeting to ask
for is the 8.2 million minus the 300
that you would
um
scope of the 300,000 doesn't include
construction.
>> Aisha, can you just get a little closer
to the
>> Thank you.
>> the the scope of the 300,000 doesn't get
us to construction. So um in to in
totality we would be asking the MSBA
typically asks that we um include as
part of our warrant article we ask for
the full amount of the con of of of in
terms of how much we need. So it will be
less whatever we've spent so far.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Thank you.
>> Bill, any questions?
>> Um I have some general questions but
I'll wait until both projects are
getting the second project.
>> Okay. I think the other thing too is
that um in terms of most the the in
terms of looking at at this overall we
we think that um normally the MSBA you
put everything that you you you need up
front in terms of the contingency etc.
Um with the idea that as we get more
into design and we go out to bid and
everything else that some of this cost
hopefully will come down. Um but this is
kind of like where we are in the
process. There's still lots to happen
between now um and finetuning of design
as well.
>> Great. Great. So um moving on to
Plymouth River Elementary School. Um
Plymouth River Elementary School was
built in 1968
um and had a roof replacement um and
repairs in 1999 or 2000. Um, in the
existing conditions found today, um,
there's widespread water infiltration,
um, through the school, um, builtup
gravel
well past its expected life. Um,
widespread deterioration of roofing,
flashing, and drainage components. Um
and there also is some um
uh bio growth as well in some areas
where there's retained water. Um there
is some plant growth as well on the
roof. Um so and that actually holds
water holds even more water. Um so that
is uh it was clear that this roof um is
in need of a replacement. Um and
additionally, um since this building has
had snow loading concerns in the past
and it does require active monitoring by
the school district whenever there's a
heavy snow um and it has caused school
disruptions, um school building
committee also had an extensive
structural evaluation performed for
Plymouth River and
um when we had last met, we had just
learned um from the Gail engineering
team that they were recommending
a um
not only structural augmentation but
also the replacement of full roof deck
um which is significantly more than what
we were expecting um in terms of need.
Um so since then we did have the school
um get their
um structural engineering team that
they've worked with to monitor Plymouth
River and check out anytime that there
was like a snow event. They would have
this structural group involved. Um
they're called Habiban Associates and
the school team had the Habiban
Associates structural engineer do a peer
review of the Yale team's um assessment
and what they found was that there are
areas of the roof deck that clearly are
overload past um the code loading. Um,
so there are areas of the roof deck that
do need replacement and there are some
areas of the roof deck that just may
need further evaluation on if it really
really needs to be replaced or it
doesn't. Um, so that is still ongoing.
Um, but as a committee we also had
discussion leading to also what Aisha
was bringing up is when we submit this
package to the MSBA, this is where the
MSBA evaluates and assigns their maximum
allowable branch. So, um, as a
committee, we unanimously approved
putting in the full amount or the the
full roof deck replacement and the
structural augmentation.
Um, and then additionally, in parallel,
as the MSBA is doing their review, we
are doing more um ironing out and really
understanding what's absolutely required
or what isn't. Um so the proposal that
we have um going into MSBA and for your
approval tonight to go into MSBA does
include all of the structural um
recommendations by the Gail team.
Um so on the next slide um just high
level um the Gail team is all
recommending a full roof replacement um
using that 80 mil
um
PVC um the same material that we'd be
using on the flat roof of South um also
using that on all of the roofing areas
of Plymouth River. Um and
ceiling and structural augmentations. So
the structural augmentations would be
right down that middle portion of both
of both ends of the building. that
middle low point. Um and then a full
roof deck replacement replacing it with
steel roof deck. Um so this would be
significant but also very strong
reinforcements. Um and since those
reinforcements
uh that is the recommended reinforcement
just to bring those areas up to code but
since they would also cover uh enabled
solar is where MSDA may be able to
reimburse um that group deck. So that's
where how we got that in and then we'd
be able to see if the MSBA comes back um
if we have any dialogue on that. So um
so that's the scope. Additionally, there
is um MAB accessibility upgrades
required here as well and also flashing
and basic repairs. Um so on the next
slide we have the overall construction
estimate
um for PRS um the roofing system um is
estimated at
um 8
6.4 performance. [laughter]
Um and then MAB um upgrades um are the
second line. The structural and ceiling
um work is really that roof deck plus
the structural augmentation together
that comes to um about 6.5 million um
and then masonry and flashing repairs.
So the total construction estimate comes
to um 13.8 8 million. Um, and then when
we add in on the next slide, adding in
our current schematic design, the um,
architecture and OPM fees,
um, miscellaneous project cost
contingencies,
um, the overall project budget um, comes
to $16 million.
And again as a committee we are
discussing how we can evaluate and just
really make sure do we really need the
full group deck or not. Um and then that
may reduce if we feel safely um continue
to use any of group deck.
Any questions?
>> A quick question just to clarify. So to
be eligible for the MSBA um
reimbursement rate of the 36.89,
is it required to do that roof deck or
are you talking about an addition
possible additional grant if we have
that structural reinforcement?
>> Um maybe I'll rewind. So to be able to
hold the weight of the roof in the snow
>> um it is many of those reinforcements
are required to meet code yes
>> and current snow loading.
So, um, that's that's really what we're
looking kind of looking at. Three steps
of like
>> what can it currently hold,
what's required for code and what's
required for code, what's required for
current snow, and then what's required
for solar,
>> right?
>> And what we're finding is that the the
requirements for meeting current snow is
actually
much more than the solar. the solar just
adds a little bit.
>> Okay.
>> Um so some of these recommended what
they would recommend to do just normally
just also happens to cover solar. Got
it.
>> Um so that's
>> um and we are untangling that like in
detail for every area of the roof just
to really make sure.
>> Um but that's um it's one of those
things that just bringing it up to what
we need also covers us.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. Great. Thank you.
>> Yeah. Questions? Are you done with PRS?
Should we take questions on this?
>> Okay. Yeah.
>> Julie, any questions on PRS?
>> Um, well, I just wanted to comment that
um that I think it's it's it's good that
in order to bring it up to code, in
effect, we basically make it solar ready
just by doing that, right? so that we
would get the MSBA grant money
potentially to cover what we needed to
do anyway to be able to support snow. So
um but my question is
I think at some point in your in your
meetings there was discussion about
having a roof uh snow melting system and
is that something that is being
considered to do that in lie of
reinforcing or you have to do the roof
decking reinforcement anyway?
>> Yes. So additional structural work will
help us untangle that for sure. Um, as a
committee, we have talked through the
the snow melt systems and they sound
really great. Um, but also have we do
have some concerns. The systems don't
last very long. So, if we did install
them, we would need to be replacing them
quite frequently and they take a lot of
maintenance or kind of finicky. Um, they
also run off electricity.
So, if we lost power to the building,
then it wouldn't keep the snow melt
system wouldn't keep up. Um, and then
even if we do have electricity
and um the snow system is running, there
is a limit to how much snowfall they can
keep up with.
>> Um, so
there is they're not a completely
foolproof way. Um but they are something
that we did we are looking at and of
course if the MSBA were to come back and
also say hey we can't cover that much or
we have some more you know discussions
um that they're they're an option that's
on the table. Um uh but we feel like
this is the best package to forward to
the MSC at this time. Um because it's
really preferred if we can just get it
taken care of structurally um rather
than chasing it through a snow melt
only. instance.
>> I would just add to that, Julie, that
our independent consultant when um she
took a look at our uh plans for a
potential snow melt, she indicated it
would be unlikely for that system system
to have kept up with the snow that we
had last winter. So, it would not have
been effective against the snow
experienced last winter. Um lesser
snowfall perhaps, but what we
experienced last winter, it would have
been unlikely we would have been in a
similar position as we were last winter.
>> Okay. Thank you. And then just one other
quick question. As you go through, you
submit your package to the MSBA and
there's going to be back and forth.
You're going to have to go to town
meeting with a dollar amount to borrow.
So, at one point, do you settle on the
like would there be any changes to these
numbers as you go through this back and
forth process with the MSBA?
>> Yes. So I maybe I can say but I
understand and I can add because you
have experience with this for other
schools as well. Um but once we submit
this um after about four weeks um the
MSBA schedules a meeting with us and our
OPM um and the design team and then
reviews what they will cover, what they
won't or they may have questions about,
hey this be considered or um there may
be some back and forth. So definitely at
that point um these numbers could be
modified especially if we made if
something wasn't covered but we made a
different choice on something that would
be um so these numbers aren't
final until the MTA board meeting when
they approve and there is an iteration
process in between and ideally we would
like to get um more of that detailed
understanding from the associate
engineering firm as we go into that
discussion as well.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> So to your question, yes, there may be
>> but in terms of the timing in terms of
now between now and town meeting, um
these are probably where we're going to
land in terms of town meeting unless
something significant happens that
knowledge that we learn between now and
then that would update those numbers.
>> Does that make sense?
>> Yeah. Yep.
>> Bill.
>> Oh, yeah. First of all, just to echo
Julie's point about the um snowfall on
the roofs, right? So, you've got we had
a winter last year where we had close to
30 in two different storms of 30 inches
of snow or more. One of them followed by
extreme cold, ice dams, roof damage. I
know the school roofs have to be flat
for the purposes of facilitating what
goes on in the school. Uh but anything
we can do to protect the roof so it will
get us another 30 40 years um I think is
a good recommendation. Um
uh so I'd start there. Um so I guess
what we're looking at based on your town
contribution numbers is we're look we'll
be looking at about 10 million for PRS
and about 5 million roughly 5 million
for South. Correct.
>> Right. And that's with I think the
36.89% 9% reimbursement rate from the
MSBA is excellent. Um, is there a chance
of any additional federal grant money or
anything uh else related to
environmentally environmentally friendly
products on the roofs that may assist
bringing that number down?
>> Not that we found super.
>> We've been working closely with Patricia
Burke. She has her finger on the pulse
of all um the available grant money. So,
she's been particularly helpful um in
discussions around the high school
project, but with regard to the
elementary project, uh MSBA really is
the game in town on project.
>> Also, we we although unsuccessful town
meeting, we were uh very successful on
reducing the cost of the proposed HCAL
from from going out to bid to the bid
coming in. The cost was reduced over
20%. I'm wondering if your OPMs have
discussed you that possibility with this
project given the fact that the pace of
municipal construction work is slowed
and with um modifications to some of the
materials we used. I mean we would bring
that 20%. Again wasn't successful but it
was successful in bringing the number
down. I'm wondering if your OPM has
discussed that with you at all or
>> Yeah. Something different on the timing
of this project compared to HCAL is that
we would be going out for bid
>> after special town meeting. So we may
find those
>> we go out the bid after
>> after the fact. Okay,
>> good to know. All right. Um the only
other thing is with the now that we're
through schematic design and the numbers
are starting to uh become more solid,
we'll need to get the impact calculator
out so people understand what's going to
cost individual households.
>> But thanks for great work.
>> Liz question.
>> Sure.
>> So I'm just curious um has the opin on
from their experience if they think that
the the maximum grant amount of 3689 is
realistic? So that is the assigned
amount
>> that is a firm amount that is not
changing. But what might change like why
that has the contingent upon
>> is that this is assuming those numbers
up there assume that everything
um in the total project budget is
eligible for reimbursement and the OPM
believes that it should be eligible for
reimbursement. Um, but where it could
change if it did is if MSBA did
determine that some things weren't
eligible, that's what would change, not
the percent.
>> When will you find that if they
determine that something wasn't eligible
and that percentage drops because of
that? When would you know that?
>> Okay. So, um,
that percent is the reimbursement rate
of eligible expenses. So the percent
wouldn't change but the of eligible may
um and we would find that out in that 4w
week review cycle. So between that four
weeks and the MSBA approval
so August 27 is our submission.
So the last week of um September.
>> Okay. It's going to be super important
to communicate as soon as you know if
that number has changed because we go to
print
[laughter]
out.
>> Yeah.
>> Sure.
>> Just one other quick question. Can you
just explain for people who may not
understand about um that that costs
they're they're not that big a cost I
would say but the the ADA MAB
accessibility
repairs that you have to do and that
doesn't have anything to do with the
roof necessarily but somehow something
is triggered right
>> yeah yeah so um the triggering event is
when the a total project um improvement
project for a building is greater than
30% of the building value
>> assessed cost
>> that the assessed cost Sorry, thank you.
The assessment class um then there's a
requirement that you bring the full
building up if there are any
accessibility code upgrades needed that
those are made um for a project of that
size. Um so for both of these projects,
we do have like a little list of what
those are. Um some of them are um
like sloping of sidewalks and entrance
it maybe some entrances wider some
bathroom um moving
>> um and
>> water bottle
>> water refill stations so and they all
improve accessibility and benefit
>> um and but they're just a bunch of
little projects um that just um add up
into this project. Um so that's the
context of what triggered that and what
we doing.
>> One of the interesting things is that
list that um Angela's speaking about it
actually came from a study that was done
by art and the town the townwide
accessibility study. Um we were able to
provide that information to the um OPM
and designers and they use that
information to be able to work into that
report. So just want to mention that as
well. Okay, thank you. Well, any
anything that we can do to fix those,
anything that's not in compliance, so
that that's that's a win. So, thank you.
>> And maybe one more benefit to speak of
having it part of this project also may
make us eligible for MSBA reimbursement
of those items as well. So, that will be
something MSBA is reviewing and will let
us know either yes, is it eligible or
not. But having that in this package
does make us potentially eligible for
keep
um we're not doing high school tonight.
>> I It's up to you. I have I did include
the heat pump options one through five
if you'd like that update but it's
um
>> it's not
we'll do that another
>> and we already put the scope article on
the right we don't need
>> okay thank you thank you for all your
work thank you to the committee and
thank you for presenting to me
>> so there is
>> so right now it's to the warrant
First agenda item eight and then we'll
do agenda item
focused on so that you can on Thursday.
>> Okay. So are there any questions or
comments from the public on the warrant
articles?
>> No. Okay. All right. I'm ready to take a
motion for agenda item number eight.
>> I'll make a motion to open the warrant
for the special town meeting and insert
the following articles.
Article A to see if the town of Hingham
will vote to raise an appropriate
[clears throat] appropriate borrow or
transfer from available funds a
sufficient sum of money to be expended
under the direction of the 2025 school
building committee for the roof system
replacement including the payment of all
costs incidental or related there to the
project at the Plymouth River Elementary
School located at 200 High Street
Massachusetts which proposed repair
project would materially extend the
useful life of the school and preserve
an asset that otherwise is capable of
supporting the required educational
program and for which the town may be
eligible for a school construction grant
from the Massachusetts School Building
Authority, MSBA.
The town acknowledges that the MSBA's
grant program is a non-entitlement
discretionary program based on need as
determined by the MSBA and any project
costs the town incurs in excess of any
grant approved by and received from the
MSBA shall be the sole responsibility of
the town. Any grant that the town may
receive from the MSBA for the project
shall not exceed the lesser 136 and 89
hunds%
36.89% 89% of eligible approved project
costs as determined by the MSBA or two
the total maximum grant amount
determined by the MSBA or act on
anything related thereto inserted at the
request of the 2025 school building
committee.
Article E. Will the town of Hangingham
vote to petition the general court of
the commonwealth of Massachusetts in
accordance with article
89 article 2 section 8 mass general laws
constitutional amendment article 2
section 8 of the articles of amendment
to the constitution of the commonwealth
for the passage of special enabling
legislation authorizing the town to
repay any bonds or notes issued to
finance projects
undertaken by the Hangingham Municipal
Light Plant over a 30-year period rather
than over a 20-year period as presently
permitted by the general laws, which
special enabling legislation shall be in
such form as the select board shall
approve to act on anything related there
relating there to inserted at the
request of the Hangingham Light Board
and to close the warrant for the special
town meeting on Tuesday, August 25th,
2026. six and to direct the town
administrator to forward copies of the
articles to the advisory committee and
to post them on the town's website
within 10 days of this vote under town
of Hingham general bylaws article 2 and
all other applicable laws.
>> Second
>> roll call vote Julie
>> I.
>> Bill
>> I
>> and I'm an I as well. Great. Thank you.
>> Okay. Next on the agenda is discussion
and potential vote regarding submittal
to the Massachusetts school building
authority of the schematic design and
associated documents for the Plymouth
River Elementary School roof project and
South Elementary School roof project.
All right. So obviously we got the
update. Is there anything else you
wanted to add?
>> Yeah. So what I gave was pretty much the
content of the schematic exam reports
and Aisha I wonder could you walk
through exactly what select board is
improving?
>> Yes. So um included in your package is
um a schematic design checklist.
Basically what the um the MSB is doing
is making sure that we cover all the
different areas that they require of us.
Um and they um and MSB is asking for
approval by both the OPM,
the superintendent um the school
committee chair and and also the um the
select board chair select board as well
too. Um another another item included in
your package is a funding agreement. Um
in terms of the MSBA wants to know
whether there are any third-party
um funding sources or other grants that
we are receiving as part of um our
funding of the project. Um sometimes
depending on what the funding source is
it may reduce the amount of the grant
that we get um and in our case we have
no other funding source. So that's just
confirmation of that. Any
questions,
>> questions, comments? Any questions or
comments from members of the public?
>> Okay.
>> I make a motion to authorize the chair
of the select board as chief executive
officer to sign and execute all required
MSBA schematic design submitts
for the Plymouth River Elementary School
roof and South Elementary School roof
projects.
>> Second roll call vote. Julie
>> I. Bill
>> I
>> and I'm an I as well. Thank you so much
for all your work on this.
>> Okay. Next on the agenda is amendment
sorry
>> to consider the amendment to the
agreement with construction dynamics for
the Southshore Country Club Pool
project. Kevin Whan,
George, David.
>> Hi. How are you?
So Chris Rody should also be on.
So thank you for having us tonight. Um
along with me is George K, the chair of
the CCMC and also David, security
procurement officer. Um, so tonight
we're here to request a uh an amendment
to the contract with construction
dynamics for the pool of $230,472.
Uh, and this is due to the um amount of
ledge that we have hit at the
construction site. Um, we will also have
an additional change order coming in um
later. We still do have a uh contingency
including all the ledge that we
anticipate of over $200,000. So, we feel
that we, you know, are still on a good
path as far as staying under the budget,
you know, um the allocated funds from
the town. Chris can, Rody can speak to
the um you know, how the project um got
to this point as far as the ledge. Um
but it was one of those things that we
uh you know, obviously we had
anticipated it based on some borings
that we had done. [snorts] Um but it's
just the quantity is a a great um much
larger amount than we anticipated.
So if Chris if you want to speak to uh
you know the uh the amounts or what have
you.
>> Thanks Kevin. I am Chris.
>> All right.
>> Hold on Chris we can't hear you.
>> Can you hear me now?
>> Yes. Thank you.
>> Great. Um so again I'm Chris Roddy the
architect um for the club on this
project. Uh as Kevin mentioned during
design there were some borings taken so
we were aware that there was a certain
amount of ledge. Um the major design
change we did at the time was to raise
the entire site five feet uh to try to
mitigate any kind of risk moving
forward. Um, and during bidding, uh, we
included an allowance of 100 cubic yards
for contractors to, uh, uh, to include
in their bid to try to cover any
unforeseen ledge. Uh, as well as, you
know, all the contractors also provided
a unit cost
for any, uh, any ledge above and beyond
the anticipated amount. Um, the amount
was 100 cubic yards. that was carried.
The amount that was has been
subsequently discovered is far surpasses
that. Um
the
uh there just were unanticipated little
knobs of ledge throughout the site where
we didn't have borings taken. um it's
very difficult to try to um really
navigate or or or quantify the amount of
glitch to begin with. Um so the thinking
was raising the uh raising the grade
five would mitigate most of it. Um
fortunately that wasn't the case. Uh
however by um by carrying a smaller
allowance to begin with and not having
that additional cost baked into the
projects
from the from the start that has allowed
Pomeroy associate associates the OPM uh
to subsequently negotiate lower unit
costs for the discovered ledge with the
contractor. So in the end um
even though it's a additional cost of
the project there were actually it will
be savings from what it would have been
had we had that larger um additional uh
uh allowance up front. So somewhat of a
silver lining, but even though it was
it's unfortunate that this amount of
ledge was discovered.
>> Right. Thank you.
>> We had I believe the additional amount
of ledge was almost 2500 tons over what
we anticipated.
>> Yeah. So that's a significant amount
which is driving the cost.
And Kevin, can you just speak to how
this is being funded?
>> So, um, we had two buckets of money. We
had the CPC funding of 550,000 and we
also had 8 million uh funded for
appropriation for town meeting at the
annual town meeting of 2022. Um we have
um just through normal course of
construction we have gone through the
550 and this will be uh you the $8
million will uh support this particular
um ch amendment to the contract.
>> Okay. Thank you
Julie. Any questions or comments?
>> Yeah. Um first of all my comment is I'm
glad that we able to renegotiate price
uh for for the further excavation. So
that's good. Um so for the contingency
we had started out with the roughly
43,000
>> correct and then
>> we have this adjustment today or the
expenses so far the 230,000 so we have
about 172,000 remaining in the budget.
Correct.
>> That's correct.
>> Okay. And then so as it was explained to
me that site work is usually the place
or the the event that takes up most of
the contingency. Correct.
>> That is correct. So we we anticipate and
especially there's not you know this is
all you know a lot of concrete work and
what have you in the building. So once
we get past uh you know the pouring the
foundations once we get past this ledge
we anticipate that there'll be very
minimal um change orders and Chris has
worked to do some slight design work to
uh to try to uh create some credits as
well with the contractor. So it won't be
a significant number but it will be
helpful for us to uh build up the
contingency. Okay, thank you. So, just
sort of follow up to that. Um,
generally speaking, and maybe you can't
even identify, but where does the
remaining continuously contingency
funding usually go in a project like
this? Or it could be anything.
>> It could be anything. We are also um you
know, we have an hourly line item for
125,000 for our budget this year as
well. You know, we have to buy equipment
to buy things. Um, you know, we have to
do landscaping, which we're doing in
house thing. So, there's several other
items that we have to do. Um, we also we
have DT DPW is building the parking lot
down below. We took several items out of
the original um budget. I mean, the
original bid that went out so we could
make sure that we got under the um a
loted the allocated money that we had
from town meeting. So, essentially, we
took a lot of things on our plate to
make sure. So hopefully we'll be able to
have some funding back so we can also,
you know, get all those uh items, those
tasks that we have to do u to complete
the project.
>> Okay, great. Well, thank you for your
diligence and work so far. Pool is one
of my favorite subjects. So
>> the foundations are being poured right
now, so things are starting to take
shape. So it's uh you know, hopefully
once we get over this hump, we'll be
we'll be doing you know, we'll be smooth
sailing.
>> Yes. excited for next summer. Bill,
>> um, no questions. As I said, this is why
we budget for contingencies and these
big projects because you're always going
to come up on um, unanticipated
costs and items. So, no issues at all.
>> And the site contractors been great. Um,
Pompio is a local company that been
they've been wonderful to work with.
>> Great. Excellent. Well, thank you for
all your efforts. Appreciate it. Any
questions or comments from members of
the public?
Great. I'm ready to take a motion. I'll
make a motion to authorize the town
administrator to sign amendment number
one to the agreement with construction
dynamics for the Southshore Country Club
Pool project valued by $230,472
for a total value not to exceed
8,636,725.
>> Second roll call vote. Julie
>> I.
>> Bill.
>> I. and I'm in as well. Thank you,
George. Thank you, Chris. Thanks, Kevin.
>> Great. I'm gonna skip ahead to number
12, presentation and potential vote to
approve Veterans Monument Eagle Scout
Project. We have John Doyle and Shannon.
Are you
How are you, John?
>> Hello.
>> Thanks for being here.
>> You want to tell us about your project?
>> Yes.
>> Um, I'll be a senior at the high school
this year, which is exciting. Um, and so
for my project,
uh, how do I
>> So, just for a little bit of background,
there are 21, uh, military and veterans
monuments here in Hangum. And I feel as
though not that many people really know
much about them. Maybe they've seen
them. Um, I certainly before this have
not known much about them. And so my
goal is to make information about them a
lot more accessible. Um I want people to
learn more about Hingham and its history
and you know just build a stronger uh
community here. Um next slide.
So uh for the plan um
>> the slides in the audience
>> slides.
>> Okay.
Um, so the plan is to compile um
information
uh about all 21 monuments to be posted
on the veteran services portion of the
town website. Um, and
then 10 of those monuments will have a
plaque placed uh with a QR code on them
so people can walk by, scan the QR code,
and all of a sudden they have all this
information about um the monument right
in front of them. Um, and the
information will be going through the
historical society as well to make sure
everything's factual and up to code.
Thanks.
Um so for the online info with the help
of the
uh with the help of the veterans uh club
at the Hingham High School as well as my
boy scout troop troop 4 hanging um we
have compiled most of the information
right now and now we're going through
edits uh some have been turned into the
uh historical society for edits and some
are very close um and the QR codes will
link to uh the information on the
veterans portion of the website as well.
So the plaque
the the plaque is um
so the plaque would be a small addition
next to the
like
it's showing
all the other things
that have
treat.
>> Yeah. So if anybody has uh wishes a copy
of the presentation that go with the
audio, we can supply it by contacting
the select board office. Sorry.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. So the um the plaque would be a
small addition next to the monument. Um
I don't want it to take away from the
monument in any way. So you know making
sure there's the right placement for
that is going to be very important. Um,
so the plaque itself will be a cast
aluminum plaque and so I have the name
of the monument as well as the QR code
for people to scan and um, if you have
your phones on you, that QR code will
scan and lead to the current page for
all the um, veterans monuments. Um, and
so I will work with the uh, Veterans
Commission to make sure that
uh, it's in a good spot and it won't
take away from the monument. it won't
subtract from anything. And also uh dig
safe to ensure that I'm not digging into
any power lines or gas or whatever.
So this is the post design which will
hold the plaque up. So it has square
tubing and then welded to the bottom of
the square tubing is the base plate. And
so the plan is to pour some concrete and
then uh drill in holes and use concrete
wedge anchors to uh secure the the four
bottom holes to it. And then at the top
is the plate with for the plaque. And
that will be cut at a 45 degree angle
and will be welded on. And with
tamperproof screws, that's how the
plaque is going to be mounted onto the
post.
So, um, any questions or
>> This seems like a great project. Thank
you, John. Certainly, um, Kingdom's
history and our military history and,
uh, honoring our veterans is very
important to us as a board and to this
community. So, thank you for bringing
this project forward and working with
um, Shannon Burke as well, historic
commission um, and to like DPW as well.
So, you have probably learned a lot
about the town through.
Excellent. Julie, any questions?
>> Uh, well, first I love this project. I
think it's really important to give out
information. You're right. People walk
by a memorial, they might not understand
who that person was. And and I see that
also when um this is not well anyway,
when you see like street signs
underneath the street sign, there's
recognizing somebody lost in a war and
you don't know anything about them. So
anyway, this is a great idea. Um, thank
you. Um just double checking that DPW is
involved with okaying the details of
this and
>> yeah so um I've met with Ashley Ber
>> um and she she is on board and um she
will be putting this into she said she'd
be putting this into her database of um
different things around the town I guess
>> to keep track of it
>> and probably maintain on an upcoming
basis.
>> Great.
>> Great. And then my only other question
is um would it be would it make sense to
also have a link on the historic town
historic commission page because
I don't know you say we had historical
society which is great but um I'm
wondering if that's worth having link
link from that page over to the veterans
page.
>> Yes, we can talk to them about that and
see if that's something they'd be
willing to do. Um because currently on
our page all it has is pictures of the
monuments and what the name of the
monuments are and there's no history
behind them. Um so that this is going to
add a full history of that but yeah I
think it would be great to link it to
the historical commission as well their
website so it's all together. Yeah I
just think someone's looking into
history in general and that would pop up
as well. So
>> thank you.
>> Great Bill.
>> Great. So um this is an outstanding
project John. Thank you for doing it and
as an Eagle Scout myself and a veteran
myself, I think this is
>> uh fantastic. Um so great great job
coming up with the concept doing it. Um
I know you said you're going to do 10 of
the 21. Pretty familiar with them. Have
you decided which 10 you're going to do
yet? You're still working on it.
>> Yes. So those 10 have been decided by
the um Veterans Council.
>> Oh, Veterans Council. Oh, great. You got
input from them, too.
>> Yes, sir. We decided on the ones that we
chose were ones that would not cause a
safety risk by someone cuz some of them
are like in an island in the middle of a
busy road. So, we don't want people
walking across the street to hit the QR
code. So, we took those ones out, but
their information on the website is
still going to be updated. So, you'll
still get the history because the QR
code actually leads you to the entire um
page that has all the monuments, not
just that individual monument. So,
you'll actually be able to get all of
them. Um, so we did ones that we thought
that would not create a safety concern
for anybody walking through county.
>> Excellent. Could you send me a list of
models out of curiosity what what the 10
are?
>> Yes.
>> Awesome. Great. Thank you. Um, and just
for perspective too, John um before you
start um when we dedicated the um
intramodal um station to uh one of our
two Medal of Honor recipients, Herbert
Fos. We actually put a QR code in under
um the bust of of Medal of Honor
recipient Foss and it's actually him
telling the story of how he earned the
Medal of Honor during the um uh Spanish
American War in his own voice. So that
little kind of a unique thing we had an
opportunity to do that with the library,
but you're not gonna you're not going to
get Major Benjamin Lincoln's voice,
unfortunately. Um, but it might give you
an idea of uh some context um to you
know honoring the um the veteran um by
going over there and listening to it. So
um so thank you. This is great. Um this
is a great project. Thank you for doing
this. Thank you to your scout master
back there too. I see him.
>> So thank you.
>> Excellent.
>> Yeah. Great job.
>> Sure,
>> John. Great project. We've been talking
about this kind of a project for a long
time. Sometimes it takes an external
nudge to move things along. So well
done. Um I would ask that you probably
with Shannon just drop off give her all
of your the specs that you use, the
companies you order the plaques from,
everything related to the plaques
because someday when you're off saving
the world, these plaques may need to be
replaced, right? And I'm going to want
to have access to make them look the
same as everything else. So if you don't
mind just leaving that information
exposed to the weather, you know, Yeah.
Excellent. Well, good luck and congrats.
Enjoy senior year.
>> Thank you.
>> We do have a vote.
>> Yes, I'm happy to make this vote.
>> Make a motion to approve and support the
proposed Eagle Scout project to install
QR codes at the town's veterans
monuments to provide the public with
historical and background information
about the monuments and to authorize the
project to proceed.
>> Second.
>> Roll call vote. Julie
>> I.
>> Bill.
>> And I'm as well. Thank you so much. Good
luck.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, Shannon.
>> Yeah. Great job.
[applause]
>> All right, we're going to go back to
agenda item number 11. Thank you, J.R.
for your patience. Consideration of
recommendations from the traffic
committee.
Reduce speed limit from 30 to 25 miles
per hour. High street from quarter mile
west of the French board intersection in
the eastbound direction of travel.
Reduce speed limit from 20 sorry reduced
speed limit from 30 to 25 miles per hour
high street from quarter mile east of
the French intersection of the westbound
direction of travel. Implementation of a
temporary basis of a four-way stop at
the intersection of North Street, Main
Street, and Furing Road. and concept
roundabout design for Cushing Street,
Main Street, and South Pleasant Street.
All right. Thank you, J.R. for all the
work on this. You want to explain uh
what's being proposed?
>> Um well, thank you for having me and uh
thank you for your time. Um
considering the time, do you do we want
the abbreviated version
and jump right in or
>> Sure, let's start there and then if we
have questions, we'll dive in a little.
>> Okay. So,
Most of this was the result of our
partnership with the Boston MPO and um
the Boston NPO had a safe streets for
all grant from the federal government
that uh Hangingham was able to partner
with them to um
identify targeted locations
for uh vision zero safety improvements.
vision zero being the overarching goal
of achieving zero deaths or serious
injuries on our roadways. Um so with
that kind of background um we went
through a full analysis of several
different intersections. The
intersections were identified by um the
intersections actually were identified
by the MO as ones that they identified
as um challenging intersections with
high accident rates and some injuries.
Uh and I actually had to dissuade them
from doing one of them that they
selected because we already had a
complete streets grant for it and that
is the main mill short roundabout. So
they were ple they were upset that they
didn't get to do the design but they
were pleased that that was moving
forward. Um but with that said the uh
locations that were selected were the
intersection of Maine Cushing and South
Pleasant. So that was one location. Um
another location was the intersection of
High French and Ward. Um that one has uh
is a challenging intersection with some
uh difficult approach angles and some
vertical and horizontal curvature that
makes visibility challenging. Um,
another intersection that we looked at
was North Main and Fearing. And then I
worked with the design team to actually
expand their scope of work and carry
that all the way up into a corridor
study of the of Main Street really
between North Street and Garrison.
Um, so approaching basically from
Hangingham downtown to Hangingham
Center. Um, and so,
um, the reports, which I'm not going to
go through in full, but were provided to
you in the packet and kind of detail all
of the different elements that were
identified. Um,
>> can I interrupt one second?
>> Yeah, I copy this.
>> Um,
I spoke with J about this today. I do I
have one. Yes.
>> Yes.
>> I think they're two different
>> Yeah, there there are two different
reports.
>> The same title, but they
>> unless you
So, we'll make sure you've got the right
paperwork.
>> Yep. [laughter]
>> So,
>> I know I have files at home.
>> Gotcha.
So um
within the the scope of that work um I
just wanted to bring bring up the vision
zero dashboard. Um this image here
actually shows a heat map of crash
patterns within H and the bright yellow
are obviously your high crash locations.
Now the vast majority of those are on
our state highways and are lo or are
located at signalized intersections.
So signalized intersections
the biggest reason it isn't because
they're signalized. It's because they
have high traffic volumes and they're at
intersections with high volumes in
multiple directions. So when you have
many opportunities for accidents and
that that's what this image reflects,
but you do see that along the 228
corridor, which is town-owned and not
state responsibility, that we still
maintain kind of uh a high rate of
accidents along that roadway. Um I
highlighted the several of the
intersections that we've already talked
about. Um, North Main and Fearing is in
that kind of blob that intersects with
downtown Hangingham, but it also picks
up 3A and then runs up Summer Street and
George Washington Boulevard. Then you've
got Main, Middle, and Short, Hangingham
Center. Um, and that's within that 228
corridor. Um, High French and Ward is
right out there on the Wayne's line. Um,
and it's kind of isolated
and kind of highlights that that is a
particularly challenging intersection
because it doesn't have the volume, but
it does have the crash rate.
Um, and then Maine, Cushing, and South
Pleasant. I'm sure everyone who has
tried to find a better way to get to
Derby has navigated that intersection
and hopefully mo mostly successfully,
but it is a difficult one. Um,
and yeah, so that kind of pieces
together. That's what I was trying to
show with that image. If you want to
kick to the next one. Um,
so one of the things that we were
uh attempting to accomplish within the
grant was to have a temporary
improvement for this intersection.
Unfortunately,
the type of work that would be required
to um make this intersection
substantially safer, but still allow
uh the types of vehicles to navigate it
that routinely navigate it. And we
actually ran a traffic study just to
double check and make sure that my
instincts were correct. but it does
actually see a fair number of um tractor
trailers. And so because of that, the
necessary
um improvements to the intersection, if
you will, took it out of the federal
scope of temporary improvement and would
have moved it into permanent
improvement.
Um I have started the process to
go ahead and prepare a design for
permanent improvements to this
intersection. Um and the reason for that
is that
um HMLP
their project to bring uh the
transmission line from National Grid in
Wemouth or Eversource Wemouth um to the
uh San Rider Road location
will navigate through this intersection
and they will be reconstructing
from curb to curb high and French
streets through that section. So rather
than have them simply pave the
intersection as it is, I think it would
be best for the town to take that
opportunity to make a substantial safety
change for this intersection
and have the plans in place to be able
to accomplish that.
Um, it would probably have to come from
a a uh common pot between chapter 90 and
HMLP's contribution for the asphalt.
Um, moving on to the the next location.
So, this is the um four-way stop
proposal. Uh this was the temporary
proposal that was provided by tool
design. And this is at the intersection
of North Street, Main Street, and
Clearing Road. One of the things that I
wanted to make sure before we advanced a
proposal for a four-way stop was to
determine whether or not the
intersection met the warrants under
MUTCD. So, we did a traffic study. We
actually did a traffic study of all four
intersections at north, south, um, main,
and central to understand what the
impact of putting a four-way stop here
would do to the rest of the uh,
intersections and to make sure that we
weren't basically um,
creating delay delays that impacted the
safe travel in the rest of downtown.
So, with that said, um what we uh what
we found is that first of all, this
intersection does meet the warrants for
a four-way stop.
Uh, second of all, the intersection at
North Street and Central Street does not
meet the warrant for a four-way stop or
three-way stop in that case.
Um
we found that the um currently
the main street approach to North Street
can see significant backups that
currently impact operation at South
Street.
So
by implementing a four-way stop, it
should alleviate the impacts to South
Street.
However, there's when we do put in these
um the four-way stop, obviously you're
going to get more delays in North
Street.
However, the queue length between Main
Street and Central Street in North
Street is sufficient to mitigate the
issues and prevent the queue
at least by modeling. There will always
be exceptions to that, but for the most
part, um I would say greater than 90 to
95% of the time, you will not see the
stop line queue in North Street
impacting the intersection at Central.
Um
so this is the temporary layout. Um, it
does provide daylighting
for pedestrians and the daylighting is
so-called. It provides better visibility
for the vehicles that are approaching,
but it does impact parking. So, this
needs to be socialized and understood by
the downtown community of what this
would entail. We would want to set a
specific period of time that we would
implement this, whether it would be one
week or two weeks, so that they could
have a real opportunity to evaluate
what the changes in parking,
what and how it impacts their business,
foot traffic, and things like that. Um,
at that point, we'd be able to take that
information
and
begin consideration
of whether or not we would want a
permanent four-way stop solution.
Um,
I think the benefits to the four-way
stop in particular are to pedestrian
safety because it is a much clearer uh
line for all all of the people entering
that intersection
who has the right away and and it makes
it much clearer that way. the um the
daylighting of course will also help by
the as the pedestrian enters the roadway
it's much clearer to approaching
vehicles that that someone is trying to
traverse the street. Um, it also
formalizes
for each of the vehicles. It formalizes
who has the right of way and you have
the ability, especially for the fearing
road to main street movement to make
that movement um safely and without fear
of being t-boned in either or both
directions on North Street.
Um, so would you like would you like to
discuss this one at all?
>> You have a question.
>> I have question going back to Ward
Street. So
>> just back it up
>> then. Um,
>> I have questions about this.
>> It's okay.
>> So um, the Ward Street High Street
intersection um, I came upon a very
serious accident there yesterday. Um,
front of a car was completely crumpled
up. Um, so I it's a tough intersection,
but I was just wondering
when you mean um permanent improvements,
do you mean like a four-way stop there
or what what would be options besides
just lowering the speed limit? Because I
know that we're think contemplating
lowering the speed limit tonight.
>> Yes.
>> But I think even at 30 miles an hour
high street, people have a really hard
time adhering to that
>> or they're not they're not well
>> sticking to that. So, I'm just wondering
if the what the 25 gets you. Obviously,
they'd be going slower, so maybe you
>> So, the the big difference there is that
you you'll have a change that people
will notice. It'll be a new sign. Um, we
may also augment that new signage um
with other types of highlights in order
to kind of um
advertise, if you will, that hey, this
is a traffic control sign. Uh, this is
traffic control change.
But with that 25 mph
drop at that point, it's also incumbent
on
um our police officers to
make that a a high an enforcement area
um and to strictly observe it. And
that's just one piece of it, but that
was something that we could do now to
try and mitigate um the conditions. Uh
it I'll never say there are dangerous
intersections, but there are certain
intersections where people engage in
dangerous behaviors
[laughter]
because they aren't they they're not
properly understanding the risks.
>> Okay. So would an idea would be down the
road in conjunction with the HMLP
transmission making it a four-way stop
or you're thinking like
and I didn't see it in the report.
>> We didn't have an an initial
um solution yet and it it may take some
more study. Um,
and I also I don't want to um
prime the well with my preferred
solution at this time. I want to see
what um [clears throat] what some other
people have for solutions.
Um
I mean I like I like simple and to me
roundabouts are simple. Um, and I think
we probably have the room to do it
there. Um, the dentist's office is a
complicating issue because we want to
maintain access for for that property.
Um,
but with all of that said, it I'm I'm as
curious as you are to see what the um
what a proper fullfledged traffic study
would would result in terms of bringing
forward for a permanent solution. Don't
I mean, the nice thing about a four-way
stop, if nothing else, is it's
inexpensive.
Um, I don't know if it if it meets the
warrants for that, but um the number of
traffic accidents may uh put it over the
edge.
That's my question.
>> Sure.
>> Okay. So, while we're here on the map of
Fearing and North, um, Yep.
>> So, [clears throat]
the black lines, you're indicating where
the actual stop place where the car
would come to stop. Is that correct? The
heavy black.
>> Yes. So, we would not relocate the uh
the post office crosswalk that we made
the RFB improvements to. Um instead, we
would move that stop line out to Fearing
Road, which is appropriate. Um, and it's
got about three cars worth of stacking
before it cars back into the um into the
crosswalk. So, there's actually plenty
of room there to uh for cars to queue up
for the stop line. Um
the
the stop line on Main Street is kind of
set back from the uh and we'll have to
evaluate that in the field to make sure
that all of these stop locations have
appropriate visibility of each of the
other approaches.
So that's the only reason that that stop
line may need to squish north a bit. It
looks really far back.
>> Yes, it I agree.
>> Yeah. Um, can you tell me what
daylighting actually is? Like what does
that mean? Is it like
>> It means that we um prevent vehicles
from parking in close proximity to the
crosswalk so that the pedestrian is more
visible as they enter the roadway.
>> Okay. So this plan hinges on removal of
parking spaces from those where those
hash lines are, those diagonal lines
are. Okay. And so it's not only just for
the
pilot, it would be the the longer term
solution.
>> Not necessarily.
>> Okay.
>> That is something that is certainly up
for discussion.
um
it can work without
the extensive daylighting that tool
proposed in my
>> okay
I think there's there's room to navigate
within that using good engineering
judgment
>> okay and final question is that just
funding for that uh that that the pilot
and maybe in the future would just come
out of chapter 90 funds or So, uh,
couple different options. One is that
the MO is actually pursuing a follow- on
construction grant to actually possibly
implement this at their cost.
So, that's our most favored option.
However, if we don't want to move on the
federal government and the MO's timeline
and we wanted to do something sooner,
um we could implement this either using
chapter 90 funds or um engineering
paving supplies from the operational
budget.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> I do I have a couple question. I go back
to the high street. Yep. Um, so I I
lowering the speed anywhere is is a good
idea in my opinion. As you might
remember, I was the one who wanted to
make everything down 25 miles an hour
and I still although you and the chief
disagree with me, I think it's would be
good to do that. But that's okay. I'm
I'm glad to see a reduction in speed
here. That would definitely help. I
agree with you that also an additional
traffic enforcement by the police
department would help. Even visibility
of a patrol car on the side of the road
slows people down. Um, but I I think
Julie's right. I think a more permanent
solution to that intersection probably
going to be needed um in the future. I
understand what you're saying, J.R.
waiting a little bit, but I think
>> it's not so much waiting. It's that I
want to put in place the right design
process.
>> Sure.
>> Totally get it.
>> Yeah. So, it's it's not that in fact I'm
pushing it along. I'm moving forward
with it. Um and the only question is I
don't know what the result.
>> Okay. Um and then going to North Street
Fairing and uh Maine. So I mean I like
this idea too. This is came up when I
many many years ago when I was the the
liaison to the traffic committee for the
planning board. Um a lot of residents in
the downtown area on Cottage Street
brought a petition forward. They were
going to submit citizen petition to town
meeting. um to make this change that
you're proposing tonight. Um but they
withdrew it uh kind of late in the
process. I'm not really sure why they
did u but it was withdrawn. So I'm glad
to see this back. Um so I'm I'm
supportive of this. I as an initial part
as an initial point I do think your stop
signs are way too far back. I mean, even
on the Fen Road one, you're looking
right to see the North Street, the North
Street, yeah, eastbound stop traffic,
that's gonna that's tight. And the way a
four-way stop works, right, is that all
the drivers see each other and they know
who got there first. They know who's
going to go next. Because every time I
do come down Main Street now, coming
coming down a little bit to the
intersection of Maine uh and south,
drivers always very get confused about
that that stop sign before the crosswalk
in front of Rud. You know what I'm
talking about? They don't know double
stop.
>> I always stop twice, but some people
don't. There was a gentleman today who
the intersection. So, some people don't
stop. I always do it to be safe, but I'm
nervous that if there's not good
visibility on the stops, people's people
people are going to kind of hesitate and
not know who's uh by law who's uh in the
queue.
>> Who has the who has the right away,
>> right? And always the first driver to
the four-way stop. Correct.
Guess they're first. They go next.
>> Generally speaking, yes.
>> Okay, we'll leave it there. All right.
So, that that's that's one my my first
point. Um but it looks like it sounds
like you're tracking on that. Secondly,
I'm concerned. I know we talked about
this on the phone. North street
eastbound traffic, right? So, east um at
North Street westbound traffic. So, you
go through the in go through the stop
sign and then if you're trying to get
trying to pull a left on the central
street, right, right by Square Cafe
beyond the church now, that's always a
little tricky because you have cars
coming at you. And I'm wondering if cars
will be backed up because you'll have
cars going the opposite way on North
Street waiting at the stop sign and then
cars trying to go left onto Central. Any
concerns from you about that point? You
know, you don't you understand what I'm
saying?
>> Yeah, I I don't have a concern on that
because that movement is not a dominant
movement.
>> Okay.
>> Um
but that the nice thing about running a
pilot
>> Yeah. is that we'll very quickly have
the information.
>> And so I you you mentioned the the the
pilot. I think two weeks is probably a
better
longer period a little bit longer period
of time than one week. Um and then my
last question to you is how do you
assess success of the pilot? like what
uh factors are you and the police
department going to look at to say okay
this has been successful or not other
than crash data which hopefully there's
not well right no I think the um the
biggest success
assessment of success is tracking the um
actual operation of the intersection
network
So when we did our intersection
assessment, we had uh traffic counters
out at each of the four intersections.
Um so all four that are right around
that downtown loop between north, south,
central, main.
And what we would we put those out again
for the same amount like for the two
whole two weeks.
>> But don't those just tracks beat.
>> No, no, no. These these are counting
turning movements and they're counting
>> um delay of vehicles.
>> So you have those up in addition to the
temporary stops.
>> So yeah
>> obviously you'll have Sergeant Kwar with
personal observations of the of the
cadence of the intersection.
>> Yeah. Okay. I mean, I'm sure they I'm
sure he'd want to have his guys out
there to just make sure that especially
during AM peak, PM peak, that
everything's moving through. Uh,
naturally, we need to keep the buses
moving for Patrick and [laughter]
and our school team. So, yeah, there
will definitely be um some close
evaluation on those elements.
My last question. Yeah.
>> Um, obviously it's that corridor is very
busy.
>> How are you going to, I guess, educate
people to this temporary change or are
they just going to come up to a stop
sign? Oh, it's fourway because because
they're going to be conditioned that
there's no stop sign there. Yes.
>> And unfortunately, people do not go the
speed limit on North Street. They tend
to travel faster than it particularly
once they get past the post office.
>> So, the day how do you Yeah. how you
propose doing it
>> with I would say a few days before you
we'd put up um
the message boards.
>> Yep. Okay, great.
>> And we'd put them around downtown
so that people depending on which
direction they're coming from would have
an opportunity. It would say
pending traffic control change beginning
and then whatever date that is and then
um see more at the town of website.
>> Great.
>> Awesome. Thank you.
>> Can I just add one quick about the
backup issue of Square Cafe trying to
take a left on Central. Could you maybe
not during the pilot, but if it became
permanent, could you hash off the road
so that cars couldn't stand and block
that intersection as there if there was
a backup queue to get to that um
intersection like you know those
intersections where
>> don't block the box.
>> Yeah.
>> Um that might be that might be an option
that we could put forward at the traffic
committee to make the recommendation.
Sure.
Um and then the last one, um
this is an outyear consideration.
Um but we were able to make a roundabout
fit at this intersection. So this is
main Cushing and South Pleasant. Um, and
we were able to do it while maintaining
all the existing driveways. Um, as well
and improving some of the sidewalk
network paths. Um, one other element
that this also allows for, um,
there are several, uh, conservation
properties along South Pleasant Street.
So last year we repaved Fulling Mill
Lane um which is the first culdeac off
South Pleasant Street. Um and
between along South Pleasant Street um
you as select board own a significant
expanse of real estate.
I could put a four-lane highway through
there [laughter] but I won't.
But um it does it would allow for a
connection of the sidewalk network very
easily to be made between Main Street
and Fulling Mill Lane. I took the
liberty of constructing um pedestrian
landings on both sides of South Pleasant
Street so that we could put the
crosswalk in crossing South Pleasant.
But this pedestri the sidewalk could now
connect from Maine to the crosswalk at
Fulling Mill Lane and then get people
safely into the conservation properties.
That's just the bigger picture, but it
would fit very nicely, this project
would fit very nicely into a follow on
um complete streets grant in which we
could very easily make the case for that
additional pedestrian
um
infrastructure.
>> Any questions on this one?
>> I was going to say I I I know that's a
problematic intersection. Uh, but I
think I'd like to see kind of how the
the proposed and select board approved
uh roundabout at Maine and um middle
goes before we start putting more in.
Um, and I'd like to get some more
feedback from the gutters in that area
as well. So, I know you talked about out
years. We're not voting on this tonight,
but correct. Kind of like to see how
that project goes for it before we make
any moves with roundabouts.
>> I agree. I know this is a problem spot
and it's come up many times. Um so I
appreciate you looking at it. I don't
think we're ready to move forward on
that tonight. Yep.
>> Um and also just back to the North
Street Main Street Fairing Road. I have
witnessed accidents there and um I know
that intersection is very confusing.
People don't understand who has the
right of way which adds to the um the
safety concerns. Um
how much I I will take public comment in
just one minute. Um have the abutters
been notified and I am concerned about
um one the change but the parking
reduction for the downtown merchants.
>> Right. So we haven't done any
significant public outreach on this yet.
Um it was just something that the
traffic committee brought forward to
propose as a as a pilot.
>> And then at the select board's
direction, we would initiate all of
those contacts, begin the process of
getting feedback, sit down with uh with
art and the and the downtown commission
um and get their input on on everything
before we move forward with final pilot
plan.
>> Okay.
I just I feel like that needs to be
socialized a little bit.
>> I do I mean the butters are aware. I've
been contacted by two of Butters. Okay.
>> Um Tom was see
some of them are aware but I agree with
you that we need to make sure they know
about it
>> and that the merchants know about it as
well.
>> Yep.
>> Do you have another question? Is it
possible to give any timeline
information about the complete streets
grant of um middle name that round up?
>> So
we recently um received the contract the
signed contract from the state. So now
we can move forward with the project uh
per se with expenditures. Um, I'm
preparing a
chapter 90 project request
to supplement the complete streets grant
to cover the additional um work that
isn't covered by the grant. Um, so the
grant will not pay for police details
and with the amount of detouring and
traffic management, that's going to be a
significant expense for that project. Um
and as it is, um our cost estimate
exceeds the value of the grant. So
there's also going to be some set aside
to make sure that we can fully complete
the project. Um, with that said, our
engineer is preparing the documents now
and they will be I think we're looking
at uh four to six weeks before those are
ready and we can get that out to
add one more thing before I close.
>> Sure. Yeah.
>> I just want to add one other thing too.
Uh, Jr. I know that um you're gonna be
moving on in your career. So, I just
want to take a quick moment here just to
um just to congratulate you and um tell
tell you how happy we are you for this
opportunity for you and your family, but
how much we're going to miss you and you
have done tremendous work in our
community. You've made our town better.
I mean, your legacy is the countless
projects that you have led, implemented,
and done so successfully. Um, I also
very much appreciate um the way that
you've interacted with residents, your
patience, um, your kindness, and just
your professionalism. So, I know we only
have you here for a little bit longer,
but just wanted to congratulate you and
thank you for your tremendous service
for our town.
>> Thank you, Bill. It means a lot. It does
[laughter]
>> that is your legacy.
>> Thought about that square.
the JR fried.
>> No, no, I don't I don't want it. I don't
need it.
>> But it's I was very happy.
>> You should be. You should be proud of
it. And thank you for your leadership
and professionalism. We appreciate it.
>> I haven't talked to you because I'm in
denial, [laughter]
obviously. So,
>> um, congratulations. Try to be a big
person.
>> [laughter]
>> Um, do you want to come up to the podium
and just if you state your name and
address for the record, please?
>> Anderson. Okay. Okay.
>> Is this about right for the microphone?
>> Yeah, that's perfect.
>> Good. Uh, Jeff Emerson, 764 Main Street.
I'm in a butter to Cushing South
Pleasant Main Street intersection.
And I have real concerns about a
roundabout.
Uh to me, a roundabout um is really
not
to me the primary choice. Traffic lights
are for a number of reasons that I'll
spell out. The first thing is footprint
of the streets. A roundabout is going to
take approximately, and I talked with JR
two or three months ago, 20 to 25 feet
of Main Street to widen it. And that
means it's going to push traffic 20 to
25 feet closer to my home. And I have
real concerns about noise,
pollution,
dust and dirt,
and health of my family.
Uh traffic lights, there's going to
there would be no change in the
footprint of any of the streets.
Specifically,
South Pleasant Street
has a triangle, two sides. on the side
uh going toward Queen Anne Corner with
traffic lights that would just be made a
two-way street.
That was a two-way street for a long
time until it was changed uh a few years
ago.
the other side of the triangle, the road
towards downtown
with traffic lights,
that could stay and traffic coming up
South Pleasant could still take a
right-hand turn. And traffic coming from
Main uh up downtown to Main Street could
still take a left-hand turn.
Traffic lights would be placed at the
side of the triangle
toward Queen End Corner. That's where
the two-way street is.
The side of the triangle towards
downtown
would just stay as is. It' just be no
lefthand turn.
>> So, that's item one. Item two is access
to the intersection.
And I don't think a roundabout
is going to be that helpful to Cushing
Street and South Pleasant with the
volume of traffic on Main Street. If
you're on Cushing Street, you have to
yield right away to all the Main Street
traffic coming up downtown.
And there are waves of traffic until the
light free and high change again. And
cars are not going to be able to enter
that roundabout from Cushing until
that's all done. So, it isn't that easy
with traffic lights.
Cushing Street, South Pleasant, both
have their turn with a green light
signal just like at Free High in Maine.
So, the access would be safe and easy.
Next is pedestrians.
I don't know how pedestrians
are going to cross Main Street with a
roundabout. There is apparently a plan,
but with traffic lights, it's easy. You
have a pedestrian signal.
This is the same at High Free and Maine.
There's a pedestrian signal. I use it
frequently. It's great. All four lanes
stop.
There is a crossing guard uh for South
School at this intersection and I'm sure
the crossing guard would very much
appreciate traffic lights where they
could just take a pedestrian signal,
everything would stop and then she could
get the children across the street.
Next is historic district. This
intersection is either very near or in a
historic district.
And a roundabout in this historic
district area is just inappropriate.
It's going to make much more of a
disruption to a historic district. And
in Hingham, historic districts are
supposed to stay the same. That's why we
have them. [snorts] Uh with traffic
lights just like High Free and Maine.
They're just traffic lights. They don't
disrupt the streetscape.
Last, South Pleasant Street, to my
knowledge, is uh a um
scenic road.
And I would consider that probably a
scenic road is a scenic road so that it
won't change.
I'm, you know, I don't know the exact
definitions of it, but that would mean
also um that traffic lights wouldn't
change anything on South L Street, but a
roundabout would. So, I would please ask
everybody to
put traffic lights on the table for this
intersection.
And it could be, you know, an option
relative to a roundabout. Uh, but I
think traffic lights would be really the
better choice.
Thank you for your time.
>> Thank you for your feedback.
>> J, can you just respond to the question
if traffic lights were part of the
discussion or are being considered?
>> So, traffic lights don't fit the vision
zero concept. So they weren't part of
tool design's toolbox in that um
because of how pedestrians are
accommodated in a roundabout um with
individual
um crossing locations for each
approaching leg. It may or egressing leg
as it were. It provides for significant
safety
um both for the pedestrians but also the
it makes it very clear
um who has the ride away at each
conflict point. So that's the reason
that roundabouts are generally the
preferred option for um safety and
efficiency over street bikes o over
stealth bikes.
>> Okay. Thank you. And I see Dear Anderson
has her hand raised. Dear Dar, go ahead.
You go back to the left.
Maybe she can.
>> It's okay. Maybe she can email email us.
>> Dear, I think we're having some
technical issues. Um, if you want to
reach out to us after the meeting or um,
send an email to the select board, I
apologize.
Are there other questions or comments
from members of the public?
Try one more time here.
Look like she was promoted.
Are you able to unmute yourself, Dearra?
[clears throat]
>> [clears throat]
>> Can you close out the box?
>> Yeah, I was say close out participants
blocks.
>> Yeah.
>> Are you seeing issue on your end,
Sebastian?
>> Uh, I'm getting
I'm not sorry.
Okay.
>> All right. Apologies, dear. We'll follow
up with you. Um All right. As far as our
next steps, um I'm prepared to take a
motion on the reducing the speed limits.
I think I'd like to wait on the North
Street Main Street pairing mode. How do
you feel about this bill? Um
just a notifications
not just not notify butters or
>> yes
>> okay fine
>> Julie
>> I understood if we agree to this then
that would set in motion the recommended
um notifications to the abuters and all
the groundwork that would need to be
done ahead of actually implementing.
Correct.
>> Yeah. And we we would still need to come
to a decision whether or not we want to
wait for the federal NPO timeline and
have them um pay for the improvements or
if we want to do this independently
using funds that were available to the
town.
>> Are you talking about North Street Main
Street and Hering Road too?
>> That's the only one I'm talking about.
Okay. the um speed limit reduction. If
if you said yes to that, then we would
implement that for you.
>> Okay. So, if we if we accept the
recommendation to implement on a
temporary basis a four-way stop, what
are the next steps?
>> The next steps would be to make a
determination. Do you want us to move
forward independent of the NPO and
federal grants or do you want us at a
minimum we can go out and do the
notifications
and um discuss
the impacts as currently proposed and
get feedback from the uh um
merchants and and and the butters. We
could do all of those people or all of
those that front end work and then come
back to the select work with a revised
plan reflecting those comments,
reflecting the comments and um decide at
that time what timeline we want to
pursue this on.
I guess I if we were to move forward, I
would want to make sure that we could
change course after collecting the
feedback. I don't want that just to be a
step in the process. I want that to be
an actual decision point.
>> Yeah.
>> Do do you know what do you understand
what I'm saying?
>> Yeah.
Um
then maybe we wait to vote.
>> Okay.
>> On that.
With that said,
>> the other steps you mentioned you can
still do
>> and just
>> so I could proceed with the
communication
notification, get the feedback and maybe
um set something up with
>> all of the downtown interests
>> and let them know what's going on.
>> Yeah. Okay.
>> Yes, I'd appreciate that.
>> What's the waiting period for that
grant? NO grant.
The pregnant pause is the indication.
>> I have no idea.
>> Okay. [laughter]
>> Is is there any urgency to implement
this temporary fix? Like are we missing
a deadline? I think is no the question.
>> There's no there's no deadline that
we're missing.
>> Okay.
>> It's um
>> it is one of those things where I like
the solution. there might be a way to
implement it reasonably inexpensively
um once we identify what that permanent
solution will be. Um, but running a
pilot that also I mean they had uh
blockouts with all kinds of like rubber
um they're kind of like area denial
things that prevent people from driving
over parking. Um but they're all like
it's all cash, right? stuff that DPW
could do with softes if we wanted to or
other things that we have in as a
stockpile. So, we can be a lot more
flexible and do it a lot more
efficiently um in a shorter period of
time if we don't want to wait for the
grant. It might not look as pretty or as
polished, but it's certainly something
that's still effective and uh and
manages to create the traffic change and
begin working on getting the results
that we want to see.
>> Okay, great.
>> Liz, can I just jump in? J.R. just as
you and we talked about this a little
bit, but as you consider continue your
transition efforts, can you make sure
right now you're the um you're the
person who understands what the board's
directives are. Uh you're going to go
out and you're going to speak to the to
the downtown uh all the neighbors down
there and everybody affected by this
project and then you're leaving. So, I
want to make sure that the that the
information
>> be followed by the tomatoes,
>> right? I I I just want to make sure that
the transition includes Pat being
brought Pat being brought up to speed.
>> Yeah.
>> Temporary engine brought up to speed
>> with what the board is is is hoping to
accomplish here.
>> Yep.
>> All right.
>> Okay. Do you want to give Jared one more
chance?
>> It's running, but I have to control it.
So,
>> all right. Um,
I'm ready to take a motion on the first
part, the speed reduction.
>> I'll make a motion to accept the
recommendation of the traffic committee
and establish a speed limit of 25 miles
per hour in the following areas of
Hangingham pursuant to Mass General Laws
chapter 90 section 17C and article 25 of
the 2022 town of Hingham annual town
meeting. Reduced speed limit from 30 to
25 mileph.
High street from one quarter mile west
of the French Ward intersection in the
eastbound direction of travel. Reduce
speed limit from 30 to 25 miles per hour
high street from one quarter mile east
of the French board intersection in the
westbound direction of travel.
>> Second.
>> Roll call vote. Julie
>> I.
>> Bill
>> I as well. Thank you Jr. That's
tremendous amount of work. Appreciate
it.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you for your feedback. Appreciate
you being here.
>> Next on the agenda are select boards
update.
>> Tom, I believe you're gonna present.
>> Yum.
where it's a little early but close
enough.
>> I was just saying that um it's a little
early for a Q1 update a couple of months
in but um I felt like we had got enough
accomplish that was worth reporting out.
Um there were three main categories of
uh of select board goals this year.
invest in the community had eight sub
goals, financial stu stewardship had
five, and effective and transparent
communication had six. So, I'll just
walk through uh each of those pretty
quick. Um the first was to define a plan
to support the senior population. Um a
lot of work actually has been uh has
been underway since the town meeting in
April. Uh we've made some physical
improvements. We've uh expanded the
programmable space into the old police
department's front desk and lobby area.
Uh we've we're actively improving the
outdoor patio uh just outside of the the
main room in the at the HCAL. And then
uh other internal uh smaller internal
improvements are underway as well. I
know the building commissioner met with
the director earlier this week um or
late last week. So progress is being
made on some of those um requests as
well. some operational improvements. I
have uh worked with the director um to
identify some operating schedule
improvements. Um she's got a series of
ideas put together for that. So um we're
evaluating those and we'll implement as
soon as we have something that we're
comfortable with. Um the uh we are also
talking about ongoing funding um funding
streams and a review of of what those
might look like as well as um a lot of
different conversations about the
long-term solutions are under
consideration um by a number of parties.
So that's all in play. It's all
happening. It's been a couple of months
of this fiscal year, but a lot of that's
been in place since April since
>> uh capital outlay schedule. uh we
actually completed that uh they've had a
couple of meetings earlier in the year
and that they're they're working on that
new schedule. Uh capital needs building
assessment and the standing facilities
committee. Um those are both goals that
we will be working on throughout the
course of the year in the potentially in
the leadup to the budget process. Uh we
haven't made a ton of proc uh progress
in those just yet in the first couple of
months, but we will like I say we will
be to the effect to the event of the um
extent that they're going to be involved
in affecting this year's budget, but
they'll be coming up here. So those
issues will be raised to the to the top
recently.
HMLP substation, you heard what we did
here tonight u with a plan for special
town meeting and a potential followup at
the annual town meeting. um the
healthcare subsidy uh study that is that
is underway. The task force has been
formed. Uh they have met, they've hired
consultants and they're actively
researching.
Um so that work is underway and I my
understanding is that they are uh on
target and early still but on target
currently to meet the deadline that was
set by town for their reports for their
reporting. uh some resiliency work over
at the at the at the harbor. You know,
this is a long-term project. I think
everyone understands that. Um this is a
multi-year uh effort. The 3A work uh is
pending hopefully uh beginning sometime
soon in the next several months. Um and
as we as we work with the state on that
FA work that's also going to uh interact
with local permitting that's actively
happened. We got some good news last
weekend down at the conservation. Um, so
again, local permitting is progressing,
3A work is progressing through the state
process and our local requirements,
whether it's water or HMLP's efforts in
that area, that's all actively being
worked on. Um, and then Lincoln School
Apartments, I know the housing trust has
been discussing this. Um so again in
progress pending uh plans but um
actively being worked on.
>> Okay.
>> The financial stewardship goals uh the
five goals there were to one was to uh
engage re-engage sustainable budgeting
task force in the update report. Again
that task force has been formed and has
met several times. Um the data updates
are complete. uh modeling options have
been um have been drafted and considered
and being reviewed by the by the
committee. We'll be um actively
discussing potential recommendations
uh in the next couple of meetings and
then with the hope of uh anticipating a
report this fall um in time to inform
next goal which was explore an updated
financial management plan. Um the the
intent of the SPTF group is to create a
series of recommendations that can
inform um in part the financial
management plan uh a next financial plan
should everyone decide they want
um and that work is also underway. The
uh the accounting department had a
number of vacancies. Uh those have all
been filled. Operational improvements
have been implemented in large part due
to Miss Dugan sitting far over to my
left struggling with Zoom and wanting to
throw a computer out the window
[laughter] but she hasn't yet which is
good sign but no she's really solved
significant issues in the accounting
department [snorts] and um and things
are going well over there. Uh we are
exploring paperless initiatives um not
so much yet but we will be soon.
[laughter]
Uh I've been told
>> yes I mean look at the reports the
reports that we had tonight like six
stacks.
>> I know again two months in but yes we
will get there and we'll get these done
as well. And then uh we I do need to
speak with John about the municipal
empowerment act and what was uh what was
a lot what was made available to us
through that act and what we can do
locally um for our
great
>> that that review will begin soon. The
last category was effective and
transparent communications. There were
six goals. One was to hold the fall
meeting with the advisory committee and
stakeholders. Um I do have uh
communications out to um to the chair of
the advisory committee. We are actively
planning for an appropriate date that is
likely going to happen in November. Um
we are also a goal one of the goals was
to create and implement the 3A
communications plan also in progress. I
have spoken several times with Mr. Fry
our engineer um about the need the
importance of this project in of this
phase of this project and he has
identified some potential solutions.
He's talked to possible vendors and a
procurement for this um is pending a
final solution and then that will be put
in place in time for the construction
for the start of construction. So, we're
still a little ways out from that, but
um the communication plan is a major
component of of rolling that that
project.
Um implementing electronic voting,
EVTFR,
based on I've been calling it. I don't
know if everyone else is, but I'm nerd.
Um that we've formed, we've met several
times. We've assigned research
responsibilities. Um [clears throat] all
the members are off doing that work and
we'll be reporting out in time to
hopefully um summar put a summary report
together for our day.
Uh we are the engaging uh we are have
been engaging our weekly video updates.
I would call that complete since we've
done eight of them regularly and I
haven't missed a single week. Um which
is great. So all good. Hopefully people
start to see the benefit of that and our
numbers increase. But um you know so far
so take a learning curve, get better at
it and you know you don't start off as a
TV show host. You got to work your way
into that role [laughter]
but I'm getting there. Um and then
scheduling a legislative update for the
select board. I have spoken with uh Joe
Mossino who is um talking to Pat Connor.
two of them will actively uh find a
date. They're actively working on
finding a date to come in and I ask for
it to be this fall. So they they're
they'll be in touch with me but hope
what we want them to cover focus on
we'll find the right date and also the
legal women voters have been in touch
with Riley and she is um she's also
helping working
for that to happen.
>> Perfect progress on
>> Yeah, lots of progress. Thank you. Any
questions or comments
from the board or people or attendees?
>> No, no one's raised their hand. Okay.
>> I will add one thing about the weekly
update is that you're looking at YouTube
views. That's one thing. But I have
heard feedback from people not watching
the YouTube video, but they're reading
the transcript.
>> And I don't think there's any way to
measure number of clicks and reads on
the transcript. But I have heard
feedback that people are using that
aren't necessarily watching the video.
don't want to see.
>> That's probably a good decision.
>> So, uh, so that's good and just
consistency. I'm just really pleased
with that.
>> Yes, it's a great idea and, um, thank
you for executing it, Tom.
>> Um, okay. Next on the agenda,
appointments.
Believe we have
>> two.
>> Um,
>> Yep. I would make an appointment. Make a
motion to appoint Thomas O'Reilly and
Terrence Granahan to the Harbor
Development Committee for a three-year
term ending June 30th, 2029.
>> Second.
>> Roll call vote. Julie
>> I.
>> Bill.
>> I as well.
>> I'll make a motion to appoint Brenda
Black to the Human Rights Commission for
a three-year term ending June 30th, 2029
as recommended by the Affordable Housing
Trust.
>> Second.
>> Roll call vote. Julie
>> I.
>> Bill.
>> I'm an I as well. Thank you to all of
our volunteers. Uh, next on the agenda
is public comment. Any questions or
comments from members of the public on
items not on the agenda?
Seeing none, if you're trying to raise
your hand, please contact us tomorrow,
but I don't see anything. Okay. Next on
the agenda, town administrator, select
board reports.
>> Katie,
>> uh, nothing from me this evening,
>> Tom.
>> Nothing today. Thank you,
>> Bill.
>> Nothing this evening. Thank you.
>> Nothing.
>> Okay. Um, and I have nothing to add
either. Thank you for the update on the
goals though. That is important. The
sustainable budget task force is meeting
this week. Um, so excited to see that
work continue. Um, if there's nothing
else, I'll take a motion to adjurnn.
>> Make a motion to adjurnn.
>> Second.
>> Roll call vote. Julie
>> I.
>> Bill.
>> And I as well. We are adjourned at 8:4
p.m. Thank you.
>> [music]
[music]
>> We recognize that taking time to visit,
call, or email our town departments to
report issues in Hangingham doesn't
always fit your schedule. Are you
looking for an easier way to communicate
with the town? Well, now there's an
easier way. With the My Hangingham
mobile app, you can submit service
requests or gain information with just a
few taps of your phone. To get started,
simply download [music] the My
Hangingham app from the Apple App Store
or Google Play, or simply scan our QR
code to [music] get the access to the
app that's best for your phone. Once
you've opened the app, select the submit
a service request button. From there,
you can choose the type of request you
want to submit, whether it's a pothole,
a fallen tree, [music] or something
else. You'll then be prompted to take a
photo of the issue and provide a brief
description.
You can also use the app to track the
status of your issue and receive
updates.
Using My Hangingham [music] puts
immediate access to town resources in
the palm of your hand, including
calendars of meetings and events,
agendas for upcoming meetings, building
permit [music] filing options, online
bill payment options, information about
our boards, [music] committees,
departments, and services.
So why wait? Download the My Hingham app
today and report [music] issues and get
information on town government with
ease.